Guide to the Ralph Henry Gabriel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ralph Henry Gabriel papers
1917-1982
MS 228
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.5
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and teaching materials of Ralph Henry Gabriel. The papers relate primarily to Gabriel's duties as editor of the Pageant of America Series and the Library of Congress Series in American Civilization, as author of history texts, as chairman of the American Historical Association's 1930 program committee, as author of several texts, and as faculty member at Yale University and at the United States School of Military Government. Also included are records kept by Sydney K. Mitchell as chairman of the Yale History Department, miscellaneous papers of Paul Demund Evans, and papers of Samuel Flagg Bemis, Christopher B. Coleman, and William K. Boyd as chairmen of the American Historical Association program committee (1927-1929).
Gabriel, Ralph Henry, 1890-1987
Conditions Governing Access
Gradebooks in Box 23, folder 394 are restricted until January 1, 2023 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph Gabriel, 1958, 1962; gift of John C. Gabriel, 1998, 2001.
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Henry Gabriel Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and lecture notes, which document Ralph Henry Gabriel's scholarly research and writing, teaching responsibilities, administrative duties, and other professional activities during his tenure as a member of the Yale University Department of History (1915-1958). Gabriel's work as editor of the Pageant of America series and the Library of Congress series in American Civilization and as chairman of the 1930 program committee of the American Historical Association is also recorded in the papers. Correspondents include Yale faculty and administration, history professors at Yale and elsewhere, students and former students, publishers, and editors.
The papers, a gift from Ralph Gabriel in 1958 and 1962*, are arranged in four series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1928-1957; II. AMERICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION FILES, 1927-1930; III. SCHOOL OF MILITARY GOVERNMENT AND YALE UNIVERSITY TEACHING FILES, 1942-1958; IV. TOPICAL FILES, 1917-1954.
*An album of Yale photographs taken during Gabriel's undergraduate years (1909-1913) has been transferred to YRG 48-A-52.
SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE, contains general correspondence files and also includes reports, manuscripts, minutes, and other materials. Yale faculty correspondents include: John M.S. Allison, Charles M. Andrews, Edward Wight Bakke, Samuel Flagg Bemis, Arthur Darling, William C. Devane, Erwin R. Goodenough, Albert Galloway Keller, Leonard W. Labaree, Frank Monaghan, Ulrich B. Phillips, Elliot Dunlap Smith, and Arnold Whitridge. Gabriel's university committee work for the Course of Study Committee of Yale College, the Committee to Study the Problem of the Master's Degree, the Committee on Universities, Yale Studies for Returning Servicemen, and other committees is also arranged in this series. University administrators who corresponded with Gabriel include: James R. Angell, Albert Beecher Crawford, George Parmly Day, Edgar S. Furniss, Carl Lohmann, and Charles Seymour.
Involvement with Yale students is reflected through reader's reports for Ph.D. candidates and correspondence with students concerning examinations, recommendations, and job referrals. Among the former students who correspond with Gabriel concerning their research and employment are Charles Keller, Thomas LeDuc, Ralph G. Lounsbury, and James Stone. In addition to summer teaching positions and sabbaticals, especially those at the University of Sydney and Cambridge University, Gabriel's service as a faculty member at the School of Military Government in Charlottesville, Virginia during World War II is also documented.
Writing and editorial work, a substantive part of Gabriel's career, is documented through correspondence with such publishers and editors as: Arthur H. Brook, Norman Donaldson, and Malcom Davis of the Yale University Press; Emerson Brown, James M. Reid, Don Stewart, and S. Spencer Scott of Harcourt, Brace and Co., Charles P. Calhoun of the Ronald Press Co., Savoie Lottinville of the University of Oklahoma Press; and Thomas Wilson of the Harvard University Press. Files from 1928-1932 focus on the publication of the series Pageant of America, while files from 1943-1957, especially correspondence with Merle Curti and authors in the series, document Gabriel's activities and interest in the Library of Congress series in American Civilization.
Correspondence with fellow historians relating to professional concerns, such as the American Historical Association, include exchanges with: Dexter Perkins, John A. Krout, Perry Miller, Guy Stanton Ford, Dumas Malone, Edgar E. Robinson, David Potter, Henry Steele Commager, Chester Destler, and Allan Nevins.
Gabriel's civic and religious concerns, and his interest in the role of religion in higher education, are reflected in files relating to Yale in-China (see also: E. Fay Campbell, Francis H. Hutchins. Oliver S. Lyford, Robert A. Smith, Richard A. Weigle, and Rachel Dowd). Gabriel's participation in the Buck Falls Conference on religion and ethics and the Laymen's Movement for a Christian World are detailed through correspondence with Weyman C. Huckabee and Thomas Steele, and minutes of the latter organization. The files for 1944-1947 include correspondence with Louis Finkelstein and Jessica Feingold on the Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion and on the Institute for Religious and Social Study. These same files include correspondence with Charles A. Russell of the Hazen Foundation and Paul D. Shafer concerning Gabriel's address "Education and the Faith of America". The 1955-1957 files document Gabriel's interest in a committee of inquiry of the National Council of Churches of Christ on the church in civic and political life.
SERIES II. AMERICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION FILES, 1927-1930, consists of files relating to the program committee of that organization. The files of program committee chairmen Samuel Flagg Bemis, Christopher B. Coleman, William. K. Boyd, and Ralph Gabriel are arranged in this series.
SERIES III. SCHOOL OF MILITARY GOVERNMENT AND YALE TEACHING FILES, 1942-1958, includes background material on the history of military government as well as source outlines, syllabi, and class rosters. Yale materials include notes, papers, and bibliographies.
SERIES IV. TOPICAL FILES, 1917-1954 consists of correspondence relating to the Library of Congress Series in American Civilization and the Pageant of America series, and files of Paul D. Evans, a Yale faculty member. Materials relating to Yale University include files of Sydney K. Mitchell, as chairman of the Yale History Department, and gradebooks for students, 1927-1947. These gradebooks are restricted until 75 years from the date of graduation. SERIES IV also includes two manuscripts on the history of religion and ideas. "Religion and Learning" (folders 389-390) is a history of the Church of Christ at Yale. These manuscripts are the only examples of Gabriel's books in the papers.
Biographical / Historical
Ralph Henry Gabriel was born on April 29, 1890, in Reading, New York, the son of Cleveland and Alta Monroe Gabriel. He earned a B.A. at Yale University in 1913 and continued his scholarly studies there, receiving an M.A. in 1915 and a Ph.D. in 1919. He served in the U.S. Army Infantry during World War I and was overseas from July-November, 1918.
Starting as an instructor in history at Yale in 1915, he became assistant professor in 1919, associate professor six years later, and professor in 1923. He held a Larned professorship from 1935 to 1948, when he was appointed to a Sterling professorship. He specialized in American intellectual history. Gabriel achieved the rank of a professor emeritus in 1958.
During his Yale tenure Gabriel served as chairman of the history department from 1931 to 1934 and as director of Yale Studies for Returning Service Men from 1944 to 1946. He became a trustee of Yale-in-China in 1922 and a fellow of Trumbull College in 1933. In 1930 he chaired the program committee of the American Historical Association.
Gabriel also taught as a visiting professor at New York University (1933), Stanford University (1934 and 1949), University of Colorado (1941 and 1942), the United States War Department School of Military Government (1943-1946), Sydney University (1946), Cambridge University (1951-1952), University of Wyoming (1954), American University (1958-1964), Tokyo University (1964), and George Washington University (1965).
Gabriel was the general editor of The Pageant of America (15 volumes), published by Yale Press, 1926-1929; in this series he wrote Toilers on Land and Sea (1926) and The Lure of the Frontier (1929) and was the joint author with William Wood of The Winning of Freedom (1927) and In Defense of Liberty (1928). He is also the author of The Evolution of Long Island (Yale Press, 1921); Elias Boudinot, Cherokee, and His America (University of Oklahoma Press, 1941); Course of American Democratic Thought (Ronald Press, 1940, revised 1956); a textbook for junior high school with Mabel Casner (Harcourt, Brace and Co., first published in 1931); Religion and Learning at Yale (Yale University Press, 1958); and American Values, Continuity and Change (Greenwood Press, 1974). Gabriel was also the editor of the Library of Congress Series in American Civilization (Harvard University Press), Christian and Modern Thought (Yale Press, 1924) and A Frontier Lady (Yale Press, 1932). He was a joint editor of Sketches of Eighteenth Century America with Stanley T. Williams and Henri L. Bourdin (1925) and of The American Mind, an Anthology with Stanley T. Williams and Harry R. Warfel (American Book Company, 1937).
Gabriel married Mary Christine Davis in 1917. They had three children: Robert Todd Gabriel, John Cleveland Gabriel, and Susan Gabriel Cunliffe.
Based on International Who's Who, 1982-1983, 46th ed., page 436; Yale Class of 1913 History, 45th year record, 1958, pp. 121-24.
United States -- Study and teaching; History -- Study and teaching; Military history; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Editors; Educators; Historians; Bemis, Samuel Flagg, 1891-1973; Boyd, William K. (William Kenneth), 1879-1938; Brook, Arthur H.; Coleman, Christopher Bush, 1875-1944; Curti, Merle (Merle Eugene), 1897-1996; Evans, Paul Demund; Gabriel, Ralph Henry, 1890-1987; Mitchell, Sydney Knox, 1875-1948; Warfel, Harry R. (Harry Redcay), 1899-1971; United States. Army Service Forces. School of Military Government; American Historical Association; Hamden Hall (Hamden, Conn.); Yale University Press; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History; Yale-China Association
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1928-1957; Series I; 5 linear feet (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in eleven sections by year. Materials are filed alphabetically within each section
  - 1928-1930
    - A - B (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Brook, Arthur H. (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Bs - Bz (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - C - Da (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    - Davis, Malcom W. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Db - L (Box 1, Folder 11-17)
    - M - Re (Box 2, Folder 18-23)
    - Reid, James M. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Reu-Z (Box 2, Folder 25-33)
  - 1931-1932
    - A - Bri (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
    - Brook, Arthur H. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Brown - Cz (Box 2, Folder 38-41)
    - D - Re (Box 3, Folder 42-58)
    - Reid, James M. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - S - V (Box 3, Folder 60-63)
    - W - Z (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Yale-in-China (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - 1933-1934
    - A - H (Box 4, Folder 66-72)
    - Hamden Hall (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - I - Z (Box 4, Folder 74-79)
  - 1937-1940
    - A - C (Box 4, Folder 80-82)
    - D - Z (Box 5, Folder 83-95)
  - 1941-1942
    - A - R (Box 6, Folder 96-113)
    - S - Sz (Box 7, Folder 114-115)
    - Schwarz, Henry F. (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Steele, Thomas M. (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - T - Z (Box 7, Folder 118-119)
  - 1943
    - A - S (Box 7, Folder 120-123)
    - Spiller, Robert E. (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - T - Z (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Unidentified signature (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - 1944-1947
    - A - Dz (Box 7, Folder 127-140)
    - E - Fz (Box 8, Folder 141-143)
    - Ford, Guy Stanton (Box 8, Folder 144)
    - G - Pg (Box 8, Folder 145-157)
    - Pargellis, Stanley (Box 8, Folder 158)
    - Ph - Stn (Box 9, Folder 159-165)
    - Spiller, Robert E. (Box 9, Folder 166)
    - Sto - Sz (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Stone, James H. (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - T - Z (Box 9, Folder 169-173)
    - Yale College
      - Allocations Committee, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 174)
      - Budget Committee, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 175)
      - Course of Study Committee, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 176)
      - Geography Committee, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 177)
      - Summer session, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 178)
    - Yale-in-China, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 179)
  - 1948-1949
    - A - E (Box 9, Folder 180-182)
    - F - Z (Box 10, Folder 183-191)
  - 1950-1951
    - A - S (Box 10, Folder 192-203)
    - T - Z (Box 11, Folder 204-206)
  - 1953-1954
    - A - Z (Box 11, Folder 207-223)
  - 1955-1957
    - A - C (Box 12, Folder 224-226)
    - Cochran, Thomas C. (Box 12, Folder 227)
    - D - L (Box 12, Folder 228-232)
    - Kandell, I.L. (Box 12, Folder 233)
    - M - S (Box 12, Folder 234-238)
    - Stewart, Donald M. (Box 12, Folder 239)
    - T - W (Box 12, Folder 240-241)
    - Warfel, Harry R. (Box 12, Folder 242)
    - Wilson, Thomas J. (Box 12, Folder 243)
    - X - Z (Box 12, Folder 244)
- AMERICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION FILES, 1927-1930; Series II; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series is arranged by year. Material for each year is arranged alphabetically
  - Program Committee
    - 1927
      - A (Box 13, Folder 245)
      - Bemis, Samuel Flagg (Box 13, Folder 246)
      - C - Z (Box 13, Folder 247-257)
    - 1928
      - A - G (Box 13, Folder 258-262)
      - H - Z (Box 14, Folder 263-272)
    - 1929
      - A - Z (Box 14, Folder 273-281)
    - 1930
      - Preliminary programs (Box 15, Folder 282)
      - A - Z (Box 15, Folder 283-297)
- SCHOOL OF MILITARY GOVERNMENT AND YALE TEACHING FILES, 1942-1958; Series III; 2 linear feet (5 Boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: School of Military Government and Yale University
  - School of Military Government
    - General
      - Allied Control Commission in Italy, 1944 (Box 16, Folder 298)
      - Basic field manual for civic affairs, undated (Box 16, Folder 299)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 16, Folder 300)
      - Civil affairs, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 301)
      - Curriculum study, 1944 (Box 16, Folder 302)
      - Relations between civil and military government, undated (Box 16, Folder 303-304)
      - Military government and the civil populations, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 305)
      - Origins and precedents, [ca. 1943] (Box 16, Folder 306)
      - History of the school, miscellaneous data, [1946], undated (Box 16, Folder 307)
      - Special orders, 1943 (Box 16, Folder 308)
      - Student rosters, 1943 (Box 16, Folder 309)
      - World War I, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 310)
      - Miscellanea, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 311)
    - Problems in military government
      - General, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 312-313)
      - Burma and Thailand, 1944 (Box 18, Folder 314)
      - Europe and Russia, 1943-1944 (Box 18, Folder 315)
      - Germany, 1943-1944 (Box 18, Folder 316-319)
      - Japan, 1943-1944 (Box 18, Folder 320-322)
      - Korea, 1945 (Box 19, Folder 323-324)
      - Malaya, 1943-1944 (Box 19, Folder 325)
      - Mexico, undated (Box 19, Folder 326)
      - Micronesia, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 327)
      - North Africa, 1943 (Box 19, Folder 328)
      - Pacific islands, 1943-1944 (Box 19, Folder 329)
      - Philippines, 1944-1945 (Box 19, Folder 330)
      - Samoa and the Philippines, undated (Box 19, Folder 331)
      - Sicily, 1943-1944 (Box 20, Folder 332)
      - Tunisia, 1943 (Box 20, Folder 333)
      - United States: Hawaii and miscellanea, 1943 (Box 20, Folder 334-335)
    - Yale teaching files
      - Notes re: 1775-1942 (Box 20, Folder 336-344)
      - Papers, 1941-1958 (Box 20, Folder 345)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 20, Folder 346)
- TOPICAL FILES, 1917-1954; Series IV; 5 linear feet (12 BOXES)
  This series is arranged in two sections: Correspondence and Manuscripts.
  - Correspondence
    - American Civilization Series, A - Z, 1947-1949 (Box 21, Folder 347-350)
    - Evans, Paul, 1917-1926 (Box 21, Folder 351)
    - Pageant of America
      - A - Z, 1927-1931 (Box 21, Folder 352-358)
      - Brook, Arthur, 1920-1927 (Box 21, Folder 359-367)
      - Brook, Arthur, 1928-1931, 1953-1954 (Box 22, Folder 368-377)
      - Outline, 1931 (Box 22, Folder 378)
    - General, A - Z, 1920-1928 (Box 22, Folder 379-380)
    - Yale University. Dept. of History: Sydney Mitchell's files, 1919-1927 (Box 22, Folder 381-387)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Religion and Learning", undated (Box 23, Folder 388-390)
    - "Christianity and Modern Thought", undated (Box 23, Folder 391-393)
  - Gradebooks, 1927-1947 (Box 23, Folder 394)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Grade books are restricted until January 1, 2023 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-037
  - "The Stories Behind the Books I Have Written," by Ralph Henry Gabriel [typescript], 1982 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-038
  - "The 1909 Diary of Ralph H. Gabriel" [photocopy] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal of motor trip from New Haven to California and back [three volumes; includes photographs], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - "Ralph H. Gabriel: In Tribute" [letters from students in honor of his retirement], 1958 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 5)